[SPEAKER_00]: This is Sāla Suttang, Samyutta Nikaya 36.6.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because an uninstructed worldling, a patujana, feels a pleasant feeling, feels a painful feeling, and feels a neither painful nor pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because an instructed noble disciple, an ārya, feels a pleasant feeling, feels a painful feeling, and feels a neither painful nor pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because what is the distinction then?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the disparity?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the difference between the ārya and the putujana?
[SPEAKER_00]: Between a noble disciple and a warling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because both feel the three types of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what is the difference between those?
[SPEAKER_00]: Different individuals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the monk said, Bhante, I'm teaching the roots in the Buddha, so, please, please explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the Buddha continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because an uninstructed ordinary person, being touched by a painful feeling, he sorrows, he's troubled, he laments, beats his breast, cries, becomes bewildered.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels two feelings, bodily and mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose, because a man was shot by an arrow, he would be shot in the wound by a second arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this way, because the man feels the feeling of two arrows.
[SPEAKER_00]: In just this way, an uninstructed worldly ordinary person, being touched by painful feelings, sorrows, his trouble, laments, beats his breast, cries, becomes confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels two feelings bodily and mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So here, the point that's quite important is the distinguishing between bodily and mental feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a common assumption that a bodily feeling is basically what people regard as bodily sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like things you perceive in your body, that are uncomfortable and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's completely not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said himself, every feeling is mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cetasika.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every feeling is basically felt on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is then... how then should be... should we understand the bodily feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it says... it says quite clearly bodily feeling is anything... any feeling that you experience mentally on account of things that you can perceive with your body or within your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, anything on account of your sixth sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, literally, any feeling that you have on account of a sight, is a feeling arisen on the bodily level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if you start grieving further, on account of that sight, and lamenting, and falling into despair, that's now the second feeling that's further mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bodily and mental are both mental, in the sense of both are felt with the mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: But difference is where they came from, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any bodily feeling is any discomfort you perceive by the body, or any comfort that you perceive by the body, internally or externally, or both.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just for the internal things you perceive in the body, nor is it just for the external things that you perceive with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's both.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have, if you have, if you're experiencing feelings on account of any of the sense, any of the sense objects, whether it's sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, anything you've seen, heard and so on, if there is a feeling arisen on that account, that is a bodily feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, both puthujjana and anārya would be experiencing that type of bodily feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that matter, in a way, but we'll see that later, arahant also experience, well, bodily feeling, but you wouldn't call it a feeling if you choose the word feeling to be applicable to the feeling that you know as puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the complete absence of puthujjana's feeling, then you can understand what arahant's feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, that's maybe a different topic.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, the difference between an ārya
[SPEAKER_00]: And between a pūtugina, the worldly ordinary uninstructed person, is they both experience these feelings on account of their senses, internally, externally, internally and externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the difference is, pūtugina mentally has no escape from that feeling, which is why he will always have
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much a second feeling on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously present there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on account of the discomfort, the pain touched through... touching you through the senses, something you've seen, heard, taste that you don't like, that frightens you and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of that discomfort, you will be suffering mentally, simultaneously with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're hit by one arrow and immediately, basically, the second arrow would shoot you in the wound.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, furthermore, an uninstructed worldly person, being touched by painful feeling, he will feel repulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Repelled by this painful feeling, the underlying tendency to repulsion lies behind this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being touched by painful feeling, he delights in the pleasure of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because bhikkhus, the uninstructed worldling, does not understand any other escape from painful feeling other than the pleasure of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it just continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having experienced something that pressures you through your senses,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're experiencing discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing the escape from that discomfort, you start experiencing mental anguish on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing the escape from that mental anguish, you then... the only thing you know is turn back to the same senses that caused you that mental anguish, and just look for things that are pleasant in them, and try to replace the displeasing things with pleasing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's definition of sensuality and sensual craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's... this is the further... this passage, furthermore, just... just basically sheds more light on how that bodily feeling should be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, it's not random sensations or things you perceive on account of a sense of touch of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically feelings you're experiencing on account of things that you perceive through your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, exactly, by not knowing escape from that, you would turn back to the same sense objects, just trying to replace them with... with those that are agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... because the eh... because... because the uninstructed ordinary person does not understand escape from painful feeling, other than the pleasure of sense desires, that's why for him, delighting in the pleasure of sense desires, then the underlying tendency of passion towards pleasant feeling lies behind this.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't understand, as it is, the origin, the gratification, the danger and the escape of those feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if he feels a pleasant feeling, he feels connected to it, as if he's bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he feels a painful feeling, he's bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he feels neither painful nor pleasant feeling, he feels bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this bhikkhu is called an uninstructed, only person who is connected, who is bound by birth, aging, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief, despair, unhappiness, trouble, who is bound with suffering, I say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to just to recap,
[SPEAKER_00]: A puṭṭhujana feels the feelings that have arisen on account of his body, on account of things... and when you say body, you mean six-sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know the body because of the six senses, and you know the six senses because there is a unit called body, that they basically consist of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, puṭṭhujana experiences a feeling on account of
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that can come through his senses, whether it's a sense of touch, like uncomfortable bodily sensations, like, I don't know, rough stone you have to sleep on, heat, cold, or even if it's something like a displeasing sight, frightening sound, a disagreeable disgusting taste, horrible smell, any of these things that you would be perceiving there on the level of perception,
[SPEAKER_00]: They do cause you, simultaneously, to be pressured by an unpleasant feeling in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel it unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is absolutely no problem with this, if, then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The patujana would know the escape of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he would understand the impermanence of the sense bases, the impossibility, the inherent lack of ownership of your own body, like fully understood that, not just occasionally thought about it, it would be impossible for him, well, he wouldn't be a patujana, but it would be impossible for him to be pressured by any feeling that would arise in regard to that which has been understood as completely impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: impossible to own, cannot pertain to you, cannot bother you, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, by not understanding that, he gets hit by the second arrow of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not just that you're pressured, but then you recognize that you have absolutely no means of escape from that pressure of that painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, literally, you can't shut down your...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can pull your eyes out, and still, you can suffer an account of absence of vision now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: The visual domain remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: The senses remain intact, even if you start trying to destroy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why when those people back in the day said to the Buddha, oh, they practice by not seeing things and not hearing things with their ears and not seeing things with their eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, you're no different than a blind and a deaf man.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no wisdom in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just avoiding because you don't know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not knowing where the problem is, you don't know the escape from the problem, you then suffer twice as much, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is suffering on account of simple disagreeability of certain sense experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bodily suffering, you can call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, because not knowing the escape, there is the mental suffering involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, think of it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's something bothering you, physically, say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is also a possibility, a certain prospect within that thing, that it might be life-threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in itself, it's not impossible to endure that certain discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could endure it, but there is a thought attached to it, that this actually might be causing the ending of your life, might kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the significance, even of that which you could bear, is now far worse, because you don't know the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know how to prevent it, and your life is at stake.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the real suffering here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that discomfort on account of body, bodily feeling that you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that mental anguish on account of not knowing the escape and recognizing that, well, if it doesn't crush you now, it will at some point in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said, by being bound to those feelings that have arisen on account of sense organs of your body, you are bound by sickness, aging, death, despair.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're bound by saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're bound by the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the real problem there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing the escape is where the dukkha is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And which is why, exactly for Sotāpanna, he becomes a Sotāpanna, he becomes an Ārya by knowing the escape from dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Four Noble Truths is a definition of escape from the dukkha that has been understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the same Putujana, who now has this mental anguish, and by the way, even the the agreeable
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure that touches your body, it still pressures you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still felt on the level of that bodily feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: We covered that in other talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, I think, if you look at the... what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The sensual... overcoming sensuality playlist.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is that even the seemingly agreeable prospect of of sensual gratification, it's first felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this sutta repeats that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything felt through the body pressures you, bothers you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the simile of the flayed cow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever way you lean or experience, it's going to be bothersome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing the escape, you get the mental anguish on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing the escape from that, you then turn back the only direction you know, which is the direction of the senses that cause the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the irony of the whole central craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sensuality is painful, you seek it, in order to overcome that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to basically replace that pain, you seek that which causes the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha compared sensual attachment to madness.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, the Upatūjanas technically are mad, because it's a level of madness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or gave the other similes, like burning yourself with the burning coal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the embers burning your skin, because it offers you some sort of numbing gratification of your sort of itchy disease and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not knowing the escape from that discomfort, you turn back
[SPEAKER_00]: To the very thing that caused you that discomfort, and then just try to seek less uncomfortable things, which is what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality is not actually pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality is simply less painful from other more painful things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And less pain from the perspective of pain, especially if you want to get rid of the pain, is going to be seen as pleasant, as extremely wanted and welcomed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what Buddha means by by patujana, not understanding any escape from painful feeling, any other escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the pleasure of the sense desires, he goes for the pleasure of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he cultivates the delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time anything uncomfortable touches him, he simultaneously... his mind is in a state of a context, basically, that values escape from that discomfort through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simply by experiencing this comfort, he already delights in comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if he's not necessarily seeking it, the mind will hold the value of comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he'll be delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha refers to these underlying tendencies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to stop delighting in comfort and stop delighting in trying to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then he goes on, the sutta carries on, then, eh... about the Ārya-sāukha, the instructed noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he's touched by painful feeling, he does not sorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not troubled, he doesn't lament.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, why wouldn't he not sorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the difference is he understood
[SPEAKER_00]: The implicit, the thoroughly understood, the implicit impermanence of that on account of which feelings have arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's important to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't say, oh, he understood feelings are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he understood that too, by proxy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need to understand, as the Buddha would say, well, that because of which feelings are.
[SPEAKER_00]: The origin of feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to understand that that already is impermanent, let alone then the feeling that has arisen on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just a question of repeating to yourself that whatever you're currently feeling, oh, this is impermanent, it's not mine, it's not mine, I can't own it, there is no sense of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just management on account of you already being bothered by the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see through that presently enduring feeling, see what it depends on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you realize, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take a pleasant or unpleasant feeling, say in this case, unpleasant feeling, on account of... so you're touched by something painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mentally, you're touched by pain on account of, I don't know, seeing... seeing somebody you really dislike, somebody that hurt you in the past, or something like that, somebody you had ill will towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just the mere sight of that person on the street and you're experiencing mental pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to now just be trying to get rid of that pain or explain to yourself that that pain is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see that your eyes are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, would you be able
[SPEAKER_00]: To experience that feeling, if there were no sight whatsoever...
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't a kind of sight and it requires your memory of the same sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still within the sight domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, are you in a position to choose what sights will arise for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: What sights will not arise for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: What sounds will arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you can exercise some sense of control, but overall, which is more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you've seen things you couldn't see, you didn't want to see, or times you've seen things you want to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's far more things you don't want to see, things you didn't plan of seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you decided you want to see them later, but the point is, you have no say in your eyes seeing or not seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not dwelling sufficiently enough of that recognition, that's how you basically start appropriating your eyes and your sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why then you get pressure on account of feelings that arise on account of sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't forget that your own very eyes are not... cannot be yours, even if you want them to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they could be yours, they wouldn't age, they wouldn't be liable to sickness, accidents and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would never stop working.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're clearly not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they just keep providing you with this content of sights, and same goes for any other organ, and you just keep taking it up all for granted, as if you created it, as if it's there because of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the impermanence that needs to be... that's the... that's the level of anicca, saṅkhara anicca, not dhamma anicca, because when you are concerned about your feeling, thinking about your present feeling, at that moment, that is the dhamma of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to see the saṅkhara of that dhamma, as other suttas say, sabhe saṅkhara anicca, sabhe saṅkhara dukkha, sabhe dhamma anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this feeling is going to be seen as not-self, when you see that that upon which that feeling
[SPEAKER_00]: Not pleasant, not worth owning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what an instructed noble disciple has understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has understood, in this particular example, the extent of the body and any feeling that can arise on account of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say the extent, I mean the extent, the nature of it, the characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it becomes inconceivable for him to grieve on account of that which cannot... it's just... it's impossible to even imagine the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason people still keep imagining the ownership of their senses, is because they never make sufficient amount of effort to think through correctly, that it cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, any effort that's made, it's usually made then on the level of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our feeling is not mine, feeling is anicca, feeling is anicca, when feeling bothers you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see through that feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: That which... because of which the feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding that saṅkharas are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's what that statement means.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, bhikkhus and ārya, being attached by painful feeling, he doesn't sorrow, he's not troubled, does not lament, does not beat... beat his breast, does not cry and does not become confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels only one feeling on account of the body, not mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose Bhikkhu's a man was shot by an arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would be... he would not be shot in the wound by a second arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this way, Bhikkhu's the man feels the feeling of one arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: In just this way, Bhikkhu's an uninstructed noble disciple, being touched by painful feeling, does not sorrow, he's not troubled, does not lament, does not beat his breast, does not cry and does not become confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels one feeling, on account of body, not on account of his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for him, being touched by painful feeling, there is no repulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no aversion towards that painful feeling, which is any feeling at that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any feeling is pressuring you, thus any feeling is painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he's not averse to pain, because he doesn't need to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would he want to be rid of the pain, when he knows that it's not his concern?
[SPEAKER_00]: He hasn't created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has a reason on its own, and he has understood that whatever arises on its own, that's why it cannot... it has to pass.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is nothing for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He cannot think, oh, this will last forever and bother me forever, which is usually that irrational thought of, oh, this this pain will be forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even people know they won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be there forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't help but keep thinking, it will be forever, so I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just this once, I must get rid of it, and then later on I'll contemplate that it won't be forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, an Ārya cannot think that anymore, because he's fully understood that whatever has the nature of arising, that's why has nature to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when he's touched by painful feeling, he has no... well, it's impossible for him to be averse towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not being averse towards this painful feeling, the underlying tendency towards aversion does not lie behind this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being touched by painful feeling, he doesn't delight then in pleasure of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if he's not, then, touched by that second pain, why would he then need to try to get rid of it when it's not there?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when it's not there, means the basis for wanting sense pleasures is not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: The instructed noble disciple understands the escape from painful feeling other than the pleasure of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for him not delighting in the pleasure of sense desires, the underlying tendency of passion towards pleasant feeling does not lie behind this.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands, as it is, the origin, the gratification, the danger and the escape of those feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: We covered in other talks what the origin is, what the gratification, what the danger and what the escape is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might search the channel.
[SPEAKER_00]: For him, understanding as it is, the origin, the gratification, the danger and the escape from this feeling, the underlying tendency towards ignorance regarding neither painful nor pleasant feeling does not lie behind this.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he feels pleasant feeling, he feels it un... unconnected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's not bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he feels a painful feeling, he is not bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he feels neither painful nor pleasant feeling, he is not bound by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This bhikkhus is called an uninstructed noble... an instructed, sorry, an instructed noble disciple who is unconnected, unbound by birth, aging, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, unhappiness, trouble.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's unbound by suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: This because is the distinction, this is the disparity, this is the difference between an uninstructed noble disciple and an uninstructed ordinary person.
[SPEAKER_00]: One with understanding does not feel a feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, painful, one who has learned much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Between the wise, clever one and the ordinary person, this is the big difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: For one who has recognized the dhamma, one who has learned much, seeing this world and the next, things that are wished for do not disturb the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And things, basically, that are not wished for, do not repel the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for him, welcoming or opposing are extinguished, brought to an end, do not exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having understood the stainless, sorrowless place, the one who has gone beyond being, understands these things correctly.